One very important thing that I noticed
when working with AI is that even if you
give enough context for an AI agent to
work on a single task, they still have
no idea about your project. And backlog
MD was basically my trial of AI and like
a challenge for myself to really try to
be as autonomous as possible and try to
let AI code 100% of the time in my
tasks. And by doing this, I realized the
most important part are the specs. And
so backlog creates the specification
about the task which is essentially the
information in that task that it can be
used as a spec for an agent to implement
that change would you say?
>> So I start code or codex and they tell
these agents hey I want to build this
feature use backlog and this CLI to keep
track of the tasks and to split it into
multiple subtasks.
[Music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Hello and
welcome to another episode of the AI
Native Dev. And you may hear in the
background there's a bit of noise. We
are at uh Devox Belgium and joining me
is Alex Gabriellescu. Um how was my how
was my pronunciation? We were saying
just off off air. It was a very British
pronunciation.
>> Yeah, this is the most British
pronunciation of my family name I ever
heard. I like it. Yeah, it's
>> We'll take that. We'll take that. So,
Alex and I are both at uh Deox Belgium
as I mentioned. And by the way, uh uh
about probably about 3 4 weeks ago, uh
we released an episode with uh Stefan
who is the the chief head god of of
DevOps. And um I am happy to say his app
is working perfectly. Um if you did
watch that session, it was a very much a
vibecoded application and he was a
little bit worried. We were a little bit
worried like oh my gosh, this is it's
very vibe coded with specifications. But
there's only one real test and that's at
a conference at DevOps to test it out
and
>> it works.
>> It's perfect. It's working very very
well. So well done Stefan. So yeah,
we're talking a lot about specri
development uh here at Deox and and Alex
um first of all tell us a little bit
about yourself cuz I think some of the
things that we're going to talk about
with with backlog and things like that
is very much is very much kind of in you
know built in a in a in a spec driven
mindset uh in terms of in terms of going
forward. So tell us a little bit about
yourself, a little bit about Batlog MD.
>> Right. So I'm a lead engineer in Vienna
for a gaming company
>> and I'm coming from an agile
environment. to using scrum uh having
all the requirements with PS uh thinking
ahead few months uh ahead with all of
the features like really thinking them
through and then there is the coding
part and right now everything happens
like uh between humans so it's uh uh no
AI no nothing just classic development
uh we have a backend team we have a a
mobile uh development team so they all
collaborate together. Uh this is uh what
I'm doing during the day, but obviously
in my free time I'm trying to learn as
much as possible about AI and trying to
keep up to date with the latest trends.
And uh backlog MD was um basically my my
trial of AI and like a challenge for
myself to really try to be as autonomous
as possible and try to uh let AI code
100% of the time in my tasks.
So
um what was the reason why I started
building backlog MD is uh I started with
side projects. I started working with
AI. I was just prompting prompting all
the time and I was just getting really
bad results. So I was basically doing
VIP coding and then I realized how what
successful uh processes I use at work
that make makes the collaboration
between humans uh effective enough to to
uh build successful gaming features and
then I try to learn from the human
process and try to adapt it to AI and by
doing this I realized the most important
part are the specs. So everything starts
with specifications, requirements, not
just about the feature you want to build
but also everything around it like
security specifications
um CI/CD specifications like just the
language that you should use like C#,
TypeScript, Java, whatever language and
you should have all of this context
uh right before you start. So in order
to be really successful with your task.
>> Really really interesting. Let's just
break that down a little bit. So, so you
you were doing a lot of vibe coding.
What typical tools were you using for
vibe coding?
>> Um, cloud MD um um code.
>> Yeah.
>> So, so and and what were the what were
the ex what examples of that those
problems did you did you kind of hit in
cord code? So the problems were
uh like a single single task problems
that would uh repeat themselves on every
single task. So what I want to mean by
this is uh I tell the agent to build a
certain feature and he reached the goal
and he managed to build this feature but
by uh going back and forth on on a lot
of things and with the next tasks I
would repeat again the same same
instructions and I would stumble upon
the same issues again and again and
again. This is the problem with vibe
coding. Basically, every time you have a
new session with your agent and you try
to build as much as possible within your
context window.
>> Mhm.
>> And this doesn't scale obviously.
>> Yeah. And as soon as you close that
window, context is lost, you have to
build that up again in your next window.
>> Exactly. And maybe you forgot the
instructions that you told him to
prevent certain issues and you have
again the same
>> problems. and a lot of the things that
you mentioned that you would put into
specs like security considerations and
things like that. How would you describe
those needs to your vibe coding tool?
>> Yeah. So obviously with vibe coding you
um can like do a lot of damage. You can
deploy some some changes some patches to
production that actually break things.
Um and you need guard rates, but you
need these guard guard rates also with
humans like the we we all use
specifications about uh security and
measures that check check uh points for
example like staging environment to test
all of these measures to to prevent
issues and with VIP coding suddenly
everyone forgot about them.
>> Yeah.
>> So what did then you kind of like
mentioned you you moved more into the
spec environment. Tell us a little bit
about that. Yes. So I started creating
markdown tasks manually. Actually before
that I started creating a huge markdown
with all of the specifications and all
of the features that I wanted to build.
Uh the problem with that it was a a huge
context and I would uh immediately
inject this context uh into the model
and uh the agent with this model will
maybe be effective maybe not and I will
not have uh good success rate and
sometimes I will have to roll back but
it would be very hard to roll back a
whole product or a whole feature
>> and what's interesting there is you're
nowhere near the context window you
nowhere near the the the maximum context
size. Yeah,
>> you're just hitting that mark whereby
the results based on the amount of
context you provide degrades massively
significantly from from that.
>> Yes, the the this agent have um feature
called compaction.
>> Uh this basically tells the agent to
make a summary of all of the previous
conversation and start with the minimum
context from that summary. But the
problem is that the instructions that
are contained in the summary are half of
the ones that you instructed him
initially and um you have to um most
likely start from scratch again because
you don't know what he he misses.
>> Mhm. Okay. Okay. So what was what's
what's next in the in the spect?
>> So what what was next? The immediate
next step was to split the big markdown
file into smaller tasks. So I would have
similar to how you have in uh Jira or in
Lina or other project management tools
single tasks that uh just define what
has to be built. And I basically
translated this into markdown files
because markdown is a universal language
that is plain text with formatting uh
that both humans and agents can uh
understand very well and agents were
actually more effective and I could
easily roll back single tasks at the
time. And you did this manually or you
did this with
>> Yes, at the very beginning I was
creating manually and I uh when I
reached around 50 manual created tasks I
I was uh like any power software
engineer I would try to automate this.
How can I automate this manual creation
of tasks? So I build backlog MD for uh
enabling this and have an easy way to
create task by uh using your terminal.
>> The best way to learn about it is to see
it right. Should we uh should we take a
look at a quick demo of backlog?
>> Uh sure.
>> Talk us talk us through it.
>> So the first thing that you will do with
uh to even run backlog you would have to
install it.
>> So you can use banan you can use mpm or
brew uh and you should install it
globally uh in your computer. Why
globally? Because then you don't have to
install it in every single project that
you're using and you can immediately use
it in every folder. So this is going to
take few seconds and
>> even on conference Wi-Fi just
>> yes exactly
>> uh this is because ban is very fast on
installing dependencies.
>> Mhm.
>> And afterwards uh you can run backlog as
as this no other instructions. This is
going to give you some uh some initial
hints what you can do with backlog. So
you can see here you can create tasks,
you can list the tasks, you can see the
board. I will uh show it very quickly.
You can also run a browser and again I
will go in detail about this and an
overview that shows what the statistics
about your project. How many tasks are
finished and how many are remaining and
the link to the docs. And the next thing
to to do normally you would want to
create tasks but because this is I'm
running backlog inside the backlog
project and I'm using backlog to keep
track of the tasks for backlog itself I
already have hundreds of tasks. So let
me show you how it looks the board.
So backlog uh gives you a component
board
>> that is configurable with how many
statuses you want. So the default ones
are to do in progress and done. And here
you can see what is going on in this
project. And all the tasks that you see
here are in sync between multiple git
branches. So backlog uses natively git
to fetch information from other
branches. So if you work with other
people uh as long as they push uh the
changes on a task. So for example, I
take over task 200 and I assign it to
myself and I put it in progress. as I
make a push on my featured branch, you
will see it also in your backlog
instance on on the main branch for
example. So this is also nice to to use
it as a collaboration tool.
>> And can you filter based on branches and
things like that here?
>> Uh so uh the the logic behind it is it's
a bit hidden from from the developers. Y
>> uh backlog should be smart enough to
find what is the task with the latest
updated date.
>> Nice. And that means is the the mo the
newest state. Obviously, if you change a
task um by mistake, this will trigger uh
that that task is the late has the
latest update version. But in normal use
cases, this should not happen. Gotcha.
Okay. And what you can do from here, you
can find the details of the task. So for
example, uh let's see one uh task that I
would like to build next. Um this one. I
press enter and I immediately see the
details of the task. So what I would
like to have in the near future is drag
and drop in the terminals.
>> Yeah.
>> So like you do in J you drag your task
from uh to-do to in progress. I would
like to achieve the same in in the this
can come board. So this is the task for
that feature is not implemented yet.
It's in to-do. And what we can see here
are the task ID, the title, some
metadata about the task, some
dependencies because backlog also
supports dependencies that basically um
prevents the the agent to work on tasks
which are not ready to be started. So
this is also important um in a
specdriven development. We have a
description that basically tell us why
are we even doing this feature. So
adding the drag and drop functionality
uh uh using shift plus arrow uh will
allow the users to to not leave this
terminal interface and to change the
progress very easily. So this is very
nice from a user perspective. And we
have some acceptance criteria which are
the core of backlog. Basically the
acceptance criteria is something that
can be testable, something that can be
easily verified and measurable and uh
basically represents the increments of
imple like the smaller increments within
this single task.
>> Mhm.
>> And whenever an acceptance criteria is
done, it will be ticked. So I will show
you very soon how that looks.
>> Uh let's open a task that has been
completed. Um
this one for example. So you can see the
status is done.
>> Uh it has been uh taken over by openi
codeex. Uh also another feature uh uh
about backlog is labels. So you can
label your your tasks and filter um
later uh by labels.
And here we can see the acceptance
criterias are all obviously implemented.
We have here an implementation plan. Uh
I will talk about uh the implementation
plan a bit later but it's part of the
spect development. You always want to uh
ask the agent how he would like to
develop this task and then you review
and then at the end we have the
implementation notes which are sort of
um permanent context what has been done
in this task. So if for any reason human
or an agent would like to see what
happened in this task, they would read
implementation notes and have this
permanent context about it.
>> Yeah.
>> So yeah, this is uh the primary
interface. We also have a task list view
uh which is this one. Here we have just
a
a long backlog of tasks. Uh we can also
um check the details and if it's longer
scroll.
We can also search for tasks. So maybe
let's
find tasks about tailwind. Uh
yeah, this this one uh there is no task
actually about tailwind but anyways
>> um you we can also filter by status. So
to-do done in progress uh priority
again. So, this is also like a second
command panel where you manage your
tasks.
>> Yep.
>> Um, and that's basically it for the UI.
Um, we also have a web interface.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh, for people that like to have more uh
um visual
uh guey for for interacting with task.
We also have a plane mode for AI agents.
Let me show you that one because I think
it's more important. So for example uh
we were looking at task 200. So backlog
task 200 minus minus plane.
This will show the same information but
in plain text. And this is what agents
should use.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I see.
>> Yeah. Okay. And and so let's talk a
little bit about I want to kind of talk
a little bit about the way in which so
you mentioned you built this a lot
through specifications and things like
that. How did you go about building
those specifications? Did you use a
tool? Did you handcraft the
specifications yourself? How did you how
did you deliver that to them?
>> So it that's quite interesting because
the first tasks I created manually. So
this kind of format I came up manually
by creating them myself.
>> Mhm.
>> And after four or five tasks I already
had backlog CLI command to create tasks.
So afterwards I just recursively started
using backlog to manage tasks about
backlog.
>> And so backlog creates the specification
about the task which is essentially the
thing or not necessarily specification
of the task but the information in that
task that it can be used as a spec for
an agent to um is it to implement that
change would you say?
>> Uh so yes and no. So backlog itself
doesn't create specifications. So
backlog is a tool that AI agents use
>> but it's not calling agents. is not
connected to AI agents by by default. So
you would have to start the flow this
way. So I start code or codex or jamina
CLI and I tell this agents hey I want to
build this feature use backlog MD CLI to
keep track of the tasks and to split it
into multiple subtasks.
>> There are some agents uh instructions
that come with backlog that tells the
agent how to use backlog itself. So
afterwards the agents will know how to
split a bigger task that you have in
mind into smaller tasks that fit
backlog.
>> But backlog itself
>> uh it should be as minimal as possible
and should not be in the way. It should
be sort of a tool that both the human
and the agent use on the side when
gotcha. So so it's claw that kind of
like determines the split almost and
then adds that into into
>> back. I see. Cool. Um so let let's talk
a little bit more about that in in in in
terms of how you would use backlog with
AI tools. Um is it when you say Claude
will use uh backlog is it using it as a
CLI and using bash is it using it as a
MCP server? Uh so for the moment we only
have CLI.
>> Okay.
>> So uh the agent instructions that ship
with backlog um let me show you uh how
you would configure this. When you
initialize backlog on a on a project uh
you will run backlog in it. You would
put the project name and here the most
important part of using backlog is to
choose the agent instructions for the
agent that you're using. So if you're
using cloud you would use close cloud MD
or now agents MD is becoming a standard.
So once you select one or many agents,
backlog will create this file or append
to an existing file if you already have
it all the instructions how to use
backlog. So it will tell cloud when the
human asks you for creating a task you
should run backlog task create. When the
human asks you to edit a task, you
should run backlog task edit and so on.
>> Mhm. Awesome. And so it adds that into
the agents MD or the cler it
automatically knows when starting this
is how it does it. This is what it
should do. Awesome. And I think you
mentioned before there was an MCP server
on its way.
>> Yes. So uh I didn't start with MCP
connection uh at the very beginning
because when I started with the backlog
in June uh the support was still um not
there for a lot of agents but recently
MCP is getting more and more momentum
and they want to also add MCP support
backlo. So in the next days we're going
to probably see it uh live.
>> Amazing. Amazing. And given that we're
probably going to be releasing this next
week,
>> yeah,
>> could even be there right now. So do
check that out on the on the backlog on
the backlog tool. So yeah, there's I
guess there's, you know, Claude and
other agents can use backlog to, you
know, break down tasks and add them into
the backlog, but also of course it's
quite proficient as a coding agent. Um,
it can go ahead and take tasks off. And
I think one of the tasks that you did
see then was potentially even worked on
and and completed by Claude. So
>> it could effectively do some work,
update the tickets.
>> Yeah.
>> Maybe something very important that I
didn't mention is that backlog's code
was written 99% by eyes because this was
my initial challenge.
>> Yeah.
>> And the only info uh files that I wrote
manually were the agent instructions. So
how to use backlo obviously
>> but afterwards every single line of code
was um written by AI. So backlo code is
really really AI specd driven AI
developed.
>> Amazing. Amazing. Cool. Let's talk a
little bit about um a key piece here
which is context. Um obviously there's
the right amount of context that we can
provide agents. If you you provide too
little it won't have enough to do a job
effectively. you can provide too much as
you mentioned and it degrades. There's
that goldilock zone of context. A lot
of context engineering has gone into
Battlelog MD. Talk us through some of
the kind of I guess the the areas that
you felt pain and some of the key
decisions that you made.
>> Yeah. So, let me start with comparison
with how humans work because I think
there
>> is also not very straightforward. So uh
I at work I me and other developers
struggle sometimes to um break down a
bigger feature in smaller tasks. And
what happens for a human when uh you
don't break it down correctly and then
the scope explodes basically you
>> uh have delays uh the then you rush and
then you have a lot of technical depth
to to solve later. So for humans this is
also a big issue but for agents it's
even more of a problem because the
agents are uh sort of like humans that
you hired 5 seconds ago
>> and you have to give them enough
information for them to immediately
start working on a task which is
something that you would normally not
expect from any any human without proper
on boarding. And this is basically what
um software engineers in the next uh
upcoming months will have to learn more
and more when dealing with AI. So how
can I give as much information as
possible about the software that I'm
building and the task itself so that the
agent will work as a as a human uh
teammate.
>> Mhm. And
>> so how did you what was the balance that
you struck in terms of too much or too
little? So I was um struggling a lot to
tell AI agents how big a task should be.
And then I had um a sort of like a a
magic um how can I say it? It was uh
unexpected.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh that I told uh Claude, hey Claude,
break down this feature into smaller
task that can each of them can fit in a
good PR.
>> Okay. And while for me a good PR is very
subjective, cloud immediately started
splitting them in the most atomic tasks
that can implement the requirements
without blowing the scope. That's really
interesting. So the
you know when we think about breaking
tasks down, what we might consider it is
breaking it down into into into
bite-sized chunks that we as people
could would think this naturally fits
together. But what you're saying there
is Claude breaks it down. Perhaps it
does it similarly, but it it it maybe
more intentionally does it whereby those
are consumable pieces of change that it
as a as a as an agent can actually
capably deliver.
>> Yeah, I think this is because uh the
training data that they have been
trained on. So probably they've been
trained on a lot of um repositories and
a lot of PR especially from GitHub
and there they could see good examples
of how much it can fit in a good PR that
can that doesn't have a lot of comments
and it's merged as quick as possible
without issues.
>> So if I was to say look I've got this
feature I would go over to Claude and
say break this feature down and add a
bunch of stuff into backlog. Um and it
would then break it down, add it to
backlog and then you would say right can
you go ahead and start working on these
ones? How would what would the next step
be beyond beyond that?
>> Obviously you would have to review these
tasks.
>> Okay.
>> Uh the the human in the loop is is
essential at this point in time. Um and
actually the human in the loop is
important right before starting the
task. So not in in my uh in my
experience the the coding part is always
done well if the task and the specs are
uh well described.
>> Yes.
>> So what I'm putting a lot of effort and
I'm trying to not become lazy is to
really review every single task.
>> Mhm. And then I will ask the agent to
come with an implementation plan because
this is also what humans do and what
some humans do and what I like to to
have in my team to if we want to build a
feature together, we will create an
implementation plan and agree on it or
maybe review it and uh build this
architecture at least on the paper
together and then someone will implement
it and this is how I effectively work at
uh team. Well, how automatable is the uh
is that process? Can you have you tried
using LLMs as a judge or using different
models to critique almost the the
breakdown of various tasks?
>> I think this is changing a lot. So
between when I started working on
backlog and today
>> uh few things have changed. So before I
would really use um one agent for
creating the tasks,
>> one agent for creating the
implementation plan and another agent
for the execution. So three a sessions
with different context window that that
they're not biased between each other.
>> Yeah.
>> Right now models are becoming better at
following a lot of instructions. So at
least the task creation and the
implementation plan could go together or
the implementation plan and and
execution do go together. uh but I don't
use specialized agents um to as of today
anymore because I feel with the latest
models that are available today this is
uh the results are good enough
>> yeah sounds good let's talk a little bit
about what could be done with AI what
couldn't be done with AI obviously the
whole thing was built with AI under your
guidance so
>> right so disclaimer
uh backlog doesn't have a production
database it's not hosted online doesn't
have any login for user information. Uh
I I was um
>> because the data because the data exists
in git repos.
>> Exactly. All of the tasks are stored in
your git repository and uh you can use
git security to to enhance the security.
So I I don't have to deal with this
part.
>> You're just using the whole of GitHub as
your database. That's what you're doing.
>> Uh GitHub or any other Git provider
>> or any other Git provider. Yeah.
>> So they implement the security for me.
So
>> um so I didn't have to face serious
production issues as I would do in my
normal job.
>> But I think this is a big limitation
right now and the next steps would be
like how we can effectively do security
reviews um performance reviews
um yeah and this kind this kind of like
guard rails for to production uh
application.
>> Yeah. And and from the point of view of
AI, you know, actually using backlog MD,
I guess how much would you say AI
empowers the usage of backlog uh MD
because it sounds like using something
like Claude really unlocks the full
features of that autonomy of breaking
tasks down, throwing it into Batlog MD,
and the terminal bases, the the the CLI
based usage fits so well with the
terminal UIs of of these agents. Yeah, I
usually just have two tabs. One for the
execution of the task or task creation
and one
>> look what is going on.
>> Uh and I don't have to leave the tab.
And this can also run in a sandbox
machine
>> uh without any GUI or any uh uh any
browser. Uh we can just SSH into into a
virtual environment and there we can run
backlog and cloud.
>> Yeah. Would you find backlog MD useful
if it wasn't for AI agents like Claude
in terms of using the the UI?
>> So, uh I heard lots of people um using
it successfully
>> uh for not AI tasks. So, they create a
task uh manually from the web interface.
>> Uh they manage them. they they um
basically have a Trello but that just
works with the Git repository and
backlog and DS CLI installed on their
computer. That's it. And they don't have
to
>> think about hosting. They don't have to
think about uh creating accounts or
anything else. It's it's very simple. So
there are some use cases where backlog
actually can be used outside of AI.
>> Yeah. But yeah, I think this uh stronger
points are when when you need to really
break down a big feature with in smaller
context windows.
>> Yeah, we we here on the podcast and at
Tesla and hearing a lot about it here at
the conference as well, we love to use
the words AI native and similar to cloud
native, it's really about rethinking how
we would go ahead and change our
processes, change our tools, change our
way of working. um using a technology as
a first class citizen. So using a
technology natively in your in your
organiza in your in your ways of
working. So when we look at some of the
if we was to redesign how we how we use
uh well how we develop software like our
basic processes and things like that um
how does an agile workflow do you feel
change with you know these new cool AI
development processes and tools? So I
think agile frameworks um the the ones
that are built today are built mostly
for humans
>> and they don't fit very well for AI
agents or the whole AI native world.
>> Uh but I think agile itself it's a very
very important way of of working. If you
look at the core principles of agile, uh
they really allow you to build solid
software maybe that you don't know
exactly how you will end up building it
at the end because that the whole point
of agile is to steer it to uh review to
have some stakeholder communication and
those are core principles are there to
stay. Um we we need to empower these
core principles and connect them with
AI. uh what I see um not being so
important in the future is like the
bandwidth calculation that comes from
certain
>> uh scrum processes because with AI we
have virtual infinite bandwidth
>> and this is this is a big change that
the companies will start to uh look into
and try to find a solution for it
because if now we have sprints and we
try to understand how much we can fit in
a twoe sprint in the future you can have
AI agents working the whole night and
can burn through five sprints until the
morning. Given that
>> they have this automatic review steps.
So I'm not talking as of today but maybe
in few months from now this is going to
be a challenge that we need to solve.
>> So what is that bottleneck now then
that's stopping that is that like you
say the fact that we're doing
>> in that world it's automated code
reviews. Today we don't have that. Is it
still that human uh human interaction
that is the bottom?
>> Yes. Currently as of today this is the
biggest bottleneck. So a human has to
tell that a certain task is done
successfully and it really implements
the specs even though um if the specs
are correct using in my case using
backlog the implementation is also uh
most of the times going to be successful
I still want to review it at least one
time and
>> I don't see right now a moment where you
can reliably have an automated review
process and automated merging into your
main branch and then you can say okay
now we can deploy this to production I
would myself not feel confident enough
for such thing but
>> assuming that the review steps security
uh performance quality all of these
things will be automated then the next
big bottleneck will be conflicts
>> uh and by conflicts I mean not just like
merge conflicts but really uh building a
product uh requires you to start
building the fundamentals then you build
layers on top of layers and then you
have the final product at the end. But
each layer is dependent on previous
layers
>> and we have to bake this into the AI
flow
>> where the agents can first of all not
clash into each other and second they
know they have to wait for certain
things to be ready in order for them to
start. M
>> and once you automate also this part
then you really have a product that you
once you give all the idea and you
verify that idea is what you expect you
let them run for hours days maybe even
weeks fully automated.
>> And what does a it's interesting what
does a retro look like? Is it is it do
we do a retro with agents? Do we have a
agent retro or do we have humans trying
to give feedback? We kind of have the
the agent retros right now. They are
called agents MD or cloud MD. I think
those are the closest thing to to human
retros. So basically
>> you finish working on a task using
backlog or any other tool. Then you
realize you stumble acu across some
patterns some negative patterns that you
want to avoid in the future. So what you
normally should do go to your ampd
instructions say
please don't do it like this or do it
like that and try to prevent these
issues from happening again. So the the
retro in the sense of looking back and
trying to do more of what went good and
do less of what went bad
>> exists
>> more or less with this agent
instructions. But if we have to think
about more structured process where
humans and AI agents are looking
together what went wrong in in a certain
product, I think there's still room to
to implement. And also what is probably
missing right now is let the agents see
the final product.
>> Yes.
>> And this is where the retrospective is
really effective. So we together as a
team we need to build a big product and
this is how it looks and this is uh how
users are using it and we did a good job
or a bad job implementing these features
and this is missing right now
>> and and that's key there. The the thing
that you said there about users giving
their feedback after something's
happened. Sprints are a nice kind of
these sprints are nice because maybe you
do some work for a week or a couple of
weeks, you give it to someone, you get
some feedback and actually in the time
you're getting that feedback, it's not
like you can accelerate and you know do
three four time 4x the amount of work
and keep adding.
>> So if we can develop and deliver so
fast, is there a risk and what is that
risk of us being able to deliver faster
than people can consume it and people
can give good feedback? Is is that is
that a risk or is that actually
something that's very easily fixed
because well
>> building is cheap now if we make a
mistake we roll back quite quickly and
you continue to build. Yeah, I totally
agree with uh with you on this and uh I
heard the story at one of my Vienna
meetups from a guy that is a plumber and
he doesn't have coding experience and he
vibe coded a small application to
calculate the the measurements for the
tools that he have to use and how to be
a good plumber. and he said he got a
quote for a few thousand euros uh from a
software developer for a thing that he
built himself in a couple of days by by
coding.
>> We're in we're in trouble cuz if
plumbers can vibe code, I can't I can't
do plumbing. We're in we're in trouble,
Alex.
>> Yeah. So, I think uh what we're going to
witness in the next months is also um
sort of a single use software.
>> Yeah. Maybe like a usable disposable
software disposable software.
>> Yeah. Everyone can just implement small
and medium size applications and they
can use them once and
>> maybe they're not necessary afterwards.
So they don't have to even have a
production quality.
>> So it's almost like prototyping change,
>> being able to say, "Hey, here's a here's
a here's closer to the main vision. Play
with it.
>> Let me know what you like and dislike."
And of course, I can just spin up, you
know, parts of those changes in my new
version. maybe change it a little bit
more. So, it's a maybe more about using
that using that that speed of
development to create pro like more
fullyfledged prototypes that we can then
actually test on folks rather.
>> Yes, exactly.
>> Very interesting.
>> One one very important u thing that I
noticed when working with AI is that
even if you give enough context for an
AI agent to work on a single task. So
you put all the information that is
necessary to start that at least will be
necessary for a human.
>> They still have no idea about your
project like effectively they start
reading the files that they have to
modify when they start working on the
task.
>> Yeah.
>> And by the time they are done that's the
moment where they really know
>> almost everything about how the task
should be done. But the task is already
finished at this point.
>> Yeah. So maybe what we're going to see
from now on is I do a quick prototype, a
quick run, let the agent ingest all the
context, not just from me, but also from
the co code itself automatically
>> build it, throw it away and if we still
have context window, we start from
scratch in a clean architect to a clean
um like domain driven design really
nicely done and maybe this result is
going to be better on the second try.
>> Right. Right. Interesting. Let's trigger
people. Alex, you ready? Are you ready
to trigger the audience?
>> Yes.
>> Let's trigger the audience. Does Scrum
even have a role in this future?
>> So,
this is a tough question. Uh I know a
lot of people are putting a lot of
effort into becoming
uh good scrum masters, good agile
coaches. And while this is very
important when working with humans, we
really need to
think at refactoring the processes the
way same way you refactor code.
>> So when you refactor code, you don't
throw away everything. You just look at
what's working and try to improve it and
to streamline it and simplify it. And
this is what we need to do also with
scrum or all all these agile processes
that are built for humans to work in a
certain way. But now suddenly we have
infinite bandwidth. We have different
processes like we said like different uh
deliverables checkpoints where the
humans have to review this and it has to
be much much faster than waiting two
weeks to have the uh the scrum review
where we present the the output to the
stakeholders.
>> We we might need two three reviews per
day in the future. So what would you say
are like the key AI scrum measurements
or or flags we need to kind of like
raise at various points? What what
what's the equivalent?
>> So what are the core fundamental uh
features of scrum? It allows you to have
uh certain deliverables in a certain
amount of time and to coordinate between
teams and stakeholders this uh
deliverable so that you can verify if
you should proceed or you have to change
things. And maybe what we can learn from
from scrum is this like create AI uh
checkpoints where sort of all of the AIs
that worked in parallel the whole night
before they reach the same point maybe
they handshake between each other and
they say okay now we need the human in
the loop
>> and afterwards we can proceed with
another batch of parallel agents but not
before the agent has validated. It's
almost it's almost an AI scrum that then
introduces a human at the right time.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Very interesting. Um let's talk a
little bit about the futures. Let's get
crystal ball and kind of say okay 6
months time, 12 months time, maybe even
longer. What do you expect to see I
guess both in and around agents or
specs? What are the major changes that
you foresee in software development uh
in and around those two areas? So we
have to look a little bit back to
understand where the curve is coming
from.
>> So uh cloud code was uh released
somewhere in March April
>> which is insane in it
>> and this is like just few months ago and
now we already have few iterations of it
and can run in parallel can use nested
agents. It's so powerful and if I think
that in 6 months it's going to be even
more powerful given that we're in an
exponential curve, it's very hard to
predict where we're going to go. But uh
the what are the fundamentals? The
fundamentals are AI agents that are
becoming more and more a hub, a central
hub that can decide what to do based on
the human interaction.
>> Mhm. So
uh I expect them to run completely uh 24
by7. Yep. So I don't expect you to have
to run code and then you give him a task
and then you stop it and then you start
with a fresh session. Uh so uh I don't
expect you to have to start clothe uh
give him a task finish the task close
him and start it start a new task in
another session. I expect to have a
persistent agent that runs 24 by7 that
is your central hub.
>> This agent should be your input point
should keep a context window that has an
understanding of what you need to
achieve as a human. But then it will use
sub agents to actually solve the tasks
and it should keep his own context
window as small as possible. So that can
coordinate sort of a team lead of of
agents basically that can spawn agents
when needed. And this agent can also be
proactive and we saw this uh recently
with some chat GPT features where you
get proactive information every morning
that are relevant for you and I think
agents are can do the same but better
because agent can use tool uh can call
tools can connect to uh other sources of
information and can maybe get trained on
your own uh data and then they can
actually actively work things that you
can delegate to him or he can come to
you and say, "Hey, you should uh prepare
for the birthday of your wife that's
coming next month." Uh I think it's a
good moment to start looking at presents
or organizing a party.
>> Yeah. When you said that, my heart my
heart beat, "Oh my god, is it next
month?" My wife, no, it's it's fine.
It's it's next year. We're good. But
yeah, super interesting. Super
interesting. Um
Alex, we could go on for many more
sessions actually. And uh the booth is
uh the booth and the and the expert area
is getting very very busy. So I think we
should we should wrap up there. But
super interesting topic where where can
where can people uh go backlog.mmd
for for learning more and and and
getting started on backlog.
>> Right. So I was very lucky that backlog.
Md uh the molda domain was excellent.
>> So now when I talk about backlog md I
just tell people just type in your
browser backlog. MD and it will
immediately show my GitHub repository so
they can learn how to use it.
>> Yeah, amazing. So check out backlog MD.
Uh Alex, absolute pleasure. Let's go and
enjoy the rest of the conference. But
for now, thanks very much for listening.
Thanks for tuning in and uh see you next
time.